Guide to the North African Jewish Manuscript Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Additional Material, 1762-1984; Accession 2016-M-067
  - Palestine
    - Letter from Ester Kadosh to her uncle, Levi Kadosh, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Letter from Ester Kadosh to her uncle, Levi Kadosh, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Part of a letter from Albert Perez, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Prozbol document, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Document concerning a rental, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 10a)
    - Catalogue of Hebrew books, Circa 1900-1940 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Libya
    - Letter regarding repayment of a loan, 1899 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Letter sent from Benghazi to the court of Tripoli concerning Eliyahu Jerbi, 1923 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Document regarding the inheritance of Buni David, 1916 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Document regarding the inheritance of Buni David, 1916 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Document regarding the property of the deceased Yitshak Shua, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Document regarding a business transaction, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Document regarding the property of the deceased Yaakov Brakha, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Document issued by the central court of Tripoli concerning a court decision, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Algeria Eastern Morocco
    - Shadar documents related to rabbinic emissaries sent to the community of Debdou, 1844-1915 (Box 4, Folder 13-16)
    - Acknowledgement of receipt of money for real estate, 1802 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Document with regard to paying off a debt, 1842 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Copy of a document concerning real estate, Circa 1850-1870 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Legal document with regard to a loan, 1878 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Document concerning a loan for a business, 1878 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Legal document concerning a loan of money, 1879 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Document concerning the purchase of a Talmud for donation to the community, 1880 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Document concerning the property of an orphan, 1881 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Testimony concerning a business partnership, 1882 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Document regarding a business transaction, 1882 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - List of donations received, 1884 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Document regarding a loan involving ben Naim family, 1887 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Document concerning decrees against Jews accused of collaborating against the king, 1887 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Document concerning a dispute between families, 1888 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Document concerning a loan, 1889 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Legal ruling regarding a financial claim, 1890 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Confirmation of transfer of money, 1890 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Two texts of admonishment, Circa 1890-circa 1900 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Document concerning a loan, 1892 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Document concerning the gift of real estate from father to son, 1893 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Ḳunṭrus kelimat ḳehal Ohran, 1894 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Document concerning a financial transaction, 1895 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Document concerning a loan, 1895 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Commercial letter, 1896 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Document affirming the importance of strictly carrying out the terms of a deed of gift, 1897 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Document concerning the transfer of property from a woman to her uncle, 1897 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Document concerning an inheritance dispute, 1898 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Legal document concerning funds for an orphan, 1888 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Letter to the community of Debdou regarding the relations between the community and the local governor, 1898 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Document regarding financial matters, 1899 or 1900 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Document concerning a financial dispute, 1899 or 1900 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Document certifying repayment of a loan, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Endorsement (hasmakhah) by the rabbi and judge of Debdou, Avraham ha-Kohen., 1900 or 1901 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Unknown lamentation and eulogy for Yosef ha-Kohen, Circa 1900 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Lamentation and eulogy for Rabbi Yosef ha-Kohen, Circa 1900 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Document concerning a loan, 1901 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Series of copies of three letters sent from Eastern Morocco, 1901 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Letter describing pogroms against Jews and asking the Alliance Israélite Universelle to intercede with the king on their behalf, Circa 1901 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Part of a document concerning the pogrom in Taza, 1902 or 1905 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Document concerning difficulties for a man who wanted to leave Debdou, 1904 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Homily on the importance of the commandment of phylacteries, Circa 1900-1910 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Letter regarding the relations between Jews and Arabs, 1902 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Letter regarding the dimensions and volume of a ritual bath (mikvah), Circa 1880-circa 1900 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Letter describing persecution against Jews and asking for help, 1903 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Letter to the Alliance Israélite Universelle seeking protection for the Jewish community against persecution, Circa 1894-circa 1908 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Letter to Rabbi Yosef ha-Kohen in Debdou requesting help settling various matters, 1904 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Letter in Hebrew sent to Avraham ha-Kohen ben Yosef ha-Kohen, 1904 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Letter asking for response to previous messages, 1905 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Letter regarding purchasing a Torah scroll, 1906 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Letter to Avraham ha-Kohen in Debdou with regard to obtaining amulets, 1907 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Report by Shelomoh ha-Kohen, explaining his decision regarding a will of a man, 1907 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Document regarding a will of a woman, 1908 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Letter to Avraham ha-Kohen, the rabbi of Melilla, regarding a Torah scroll, 1908 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Halakhic novellae and Talmudic commentary written by a learned man, 1910 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Letter to Avraham ha-Kohen written during the Ten Days of Repentance, 1910 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Letter to Avraham ha-Kohen in Debdou concerning family and other matters, 1910 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Letter affirming the validity of a translated document, 1911 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Letter to Avraham ha-Kohen in Debdou, 1911 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Letter sent by David ha-Kohen Skali to Avraham ha-Kohen with regard to a Torah scroll, 1911 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Copies of two letters sent to Avraham ha-Kohen in Debdou asking him to use his authority to enforce a loan agreement, 1911 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Letter to Avraham ha-Kohen in Debdou requesting French documents, 1911 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Letter to Avraham ha-Kohen in Debdou, 1914 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Letter to Avraham ha-Kohen, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Letter with news about various relatives, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Document assigning a messenger to deliver a bill of divorce, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Document assigning a messenger to deliver a bill of divorce, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Commercial document, 1931 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Prayers of supplication, Circa 1850-1900 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Letter to the chief rabbi of Algeria requesting a rabbi and a teacher for the community of Ghardaïa, 1857 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Letter regarding a rabbinic emissary sent to Ghardaïa and the surrounding villages, 1859, 1860 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Document regarding land purchased by Yosef Elbaz from the community of Ghardaïa, 1887 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Document concerning a man whose family did not participate in the fundraising for the synagogue of the community, 1887 or 1888 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Letter to Yosef Elbaz regarding books and reporting on troubles in Casablanca, 1904 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Letter to Yosef Elbaz regarding various subjects concerning the family, 1905 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Copy of a ketubah, 1906 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Letter to Yosef Elbaz from his brother Shalem in Jerusalem with request for financial help, 1908 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Letter to Yosef Elbaz from his brother Shalem, who still did not receive money, 1909 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Letter to Yosef Elbaz from his brother Avraham dicussing problems with mail, Circa 1910 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Letter to Ben Tsiyon Elbaz reporting that the money sent by mail had not arrived, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Two letters to Ben Tsiyon Elbaz from Avraham ha-Kohen, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Ketubot
    - Replacement ketubah, 1873 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Copy of a ketubah of Yissakhar Hakhmon, 1922 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Legal document regarding a woman's property, 1924 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Copy of a ketubah, 1924 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Ketubah from the village of Ayt Immi in the Marrakech region, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Copy of a ketubah, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Unfilled form of a ketubah, Undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Ketubah: Taourirt, Morocco, 20 Elul 5[6]85 (September 9, 1925) (Box 5, Folder 3)